Guide to the Alpha Tau Delta Lambda Chapter records 1940-1980
Montana Historical Society
Alpha Tau Delta. Lambda Chapter records
1940-1980
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 304
Alpha Tau Delta. Lambda Chapter (Mont.)
1.5 linear feet
These records of the Lambda chapter of Alpha Tau Delta, an undergraduate student nurses honor society at Montana State University, consist of records of the statewide organization, several local organizations, the alumnae organization, and the national organization. The records include correspondence, financial records, membership records, minutes, organizational records, publications, reports, and miscellany.
Historical Note:
Alpha Tau Delta is a professional fraternity for persons in collegiate nursing. It was founded February 15, 1921, at the University of California and was incorporated the same year. Through the years more than 30 college chapters were organized.
The purposes of Alpha Tau Delta were: to further higher professional standards for the nursing profession; to inaugurate projects that strengthen the specific field of professional nursing; to develop character and leadership, encourage high ethical standards of professional conduct in which members may develop sound professional philosophies; to encourage excellence of individual performance and develop the highest possible scholastic attainments; to organize the social life of its members as a contributing factor in their educational program, and maintain an intrafraternity spirit of cooperation; and to form a close bond of friendship, fellowship, mutual helpfulness, and understanding among college students in the nursing profession.
Authorized college chapters conferred membership in the fraternity. There were two chapters at Montana State University: Lambda Chapter for academically qualified undergraduate nursing students, and Lambda Pi Chapter for alumnae.
The original charter for the Lambda Chapter was issued to Montana State College on April 27, 1940, when initiation and installation of members also took place. The first annual meeting appears to have been held on June 2, 1956. Divisions of Alpha Tau Delta were organized in Butte, Billings, Bozeman, and Great Falls. In 1982 Alpha Tau Delta was replaced at Montana State University by Montana's Zeta Upsilon Chapter of Sigma Theta Tau.
Lambda Pi Chapter was organized in 1963 with stated purposes: to inaugurate projects that enrich the individual alumnae and specific fields of professional nursing; to assist Lambda Chapter in their stated purposes; and to provide stimulation and guidance to Lambda Chapter. The alumnae chapter elected its own officers and held quarterly meetings.
Records consist of Lambda Chapter records, including several local branches, plus Lambda Pi Chapter records (the alumnae chapter), and a few national items.
Statewide records include biographical sketches on early members; interoffice correspondence (1955-1980); general correspondence (1956-1979); financial records (1948-1977); minutes (1956-1978); organizational records (1940-1977) including the charter, constitution and bylaws, member and officer lists, policies and procedures, and rituals; press releases (1973); a newsletter (1961-1978) entitled Lambda Hotlines; reports (1956-1973) to the national organization; subject files (1961-1977); miscellany; and clippings (1955-1973).
There are small subgroups for the Billings Deaconess Division, the Bozeman Division, the Butte Division, the Great Falls Deaconess Division, the Lambda Pi Chapter [alumni], and the national organization.
Arranged by subgroup and series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Alpha Tau Delta. Lambda Chapter (Mont.)
Medicine--Societies, etc.--Montana.; Nursing--Study and teaching--Montana.; Medicine--Study and teaching--Montana.
Nurses--Montana.
Montana; Medicine and Health
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Alpha Tau Delta. Lambda Chapter
  - Biographical Materials
    - Biographical sketches and notes re early and deceased members (includes E. Augusta Ariss, Shirley Joann Cox, June Leona Crane, Joan Egnew, Rilla Einfeldt, Marjorie Ellen Hart, Blanche M. Fuller, Sheryl Gee, Yvonne Knutson, Mary Peterson, Jo Ann Phillips, Ida Marie Randash, Janice M. Schoen, Oddlaug Stene, Barbara Ann West, Bonnie Jean Wham), undated (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Interoffice Correspondence
    - Advisors (includes Shirley Duderstadt, Jeanne R. Claus, Barbara Hauf, Milly Gutkoski), 1958-1980 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Memoranda to membership, 1955-1979 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (includes Miriam Fay Furlong, Jo Ann Phillips, Eleanor H. Newby, Avis Peterson, Merlyn Willett, Barbara Hauf, LaVerne Rocereto, Marilyn J. McDaniel, Mollie Hatch, Myra Ridder, Loretta Birken Tagress, Montana State University, National Alpha Tau Delta), 1956-1979 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Financial Records
    - Journal, 1948-1956 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Miscellaneous (includes financial reports, applications for tax-exempt status, etc.), 1956-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Minutes
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Chapter minutes, 1956-1978 (Box-folder 1 / 8-9)
  - Organization
    - Charter, 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1964, 1967 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - Membership lists, 1940-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Officers lists, 1956-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - Policies, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - Procedures and rituals, undated (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Roll book, 1940-1959 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Press Releases
    - News releases (re meetings, admission of men), 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Printed Materials
    - Lambda Hotlines newsletter [title varies slightly], 1961-1978 (Box-folder 2 / 2-3)
  - Reports
    - Semi-annual chapter reports to National, 1956-1973 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Subject Files
    - Artwork, undated (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - Awards, 1961-1975, undated (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - Epilepsy project, 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Hosting of national convention, 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Peace Corps project, 1977 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Scholarships, undated (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Women's Day project, 1974-1975, undated (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Miscellany
    - Letterheads, envelopes, booklet, song, undated (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Clippings
    - Re inductions, meetings, etc., 1955-1973 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
- Billings Deaconess Division
  - Minutes
    - Division minutes, 1957-1963, 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
- Bozeman Division
  - Financial Records
    - Journal, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Minutes
    - Division minutes [some are in book, some are loose], 1953-1970 (Box-folder 2 / 16-18)
- Butte Division
  - Reports
    - Report on officers, 1977 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
- Great Falls Deaconess Division
  - Financial Records
    - Journal; check registers, 1956-1978 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
  - Minutes
    - Division minutes, 1961, 1977 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - Subject Files
    - Fund raising, 1962-1971 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
- Lambda Pi Chapter
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (includes Lois Landis, Barbara E. Langlois, B.K. Jordan, Herva Simpson, Ruth McCullough, Ethel Nelson, C. Hazel Sorenson, Merlyn Willett, Milly Gutkoski), 1959-1974 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Financial Records
    - Dues paid (also includes list of letters sent, 1970), 1964-1970 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Minutes
    - Chapter minutes, 1960-1973 (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Organization
    - Constitution, 1963 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - Reports
    - Semi-annual reports to National, 1956-1974 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
- National Alpha Tau Delta
  - Printed Materials
    - Cap'tions newsletter, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - Handbooks, pledge book, directories, 1958-1975, undated (Box-folder 3 / 11)